Guide to the Center for Advanced Studies Records, 1958 - 1969
Center for Advanced Studies Records, 1958 - 1969
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Center for Advanced Studies.
1000-137
13.25
25
The Center for Advanced Studies (CAS) was founded at Wesleyan University in 1959 and existed until 1969. The CAS invited fellows to reside at Wesleyan and participate in the intellectual life of the campus. Each year, the fellows were a diverse group of academics, scientists, social scientists, writers, artists, and other intellectuals. Sigmund Neumann served as director of CAS from 1959-1962, Paul Horgan from 1962 until 1967, and Phillip Hallie as acting director from 1967-1969. Victor Butterfield, president of Wesleyan University until 1967, was actively involved in the Center.
The Center for Advanced Studies Records include general files, annual reports, publicity, photographs, a scrapbook, lists of fellows and those under consideration as fellows, and recordings. Throughout the collection, documentation from 1967 to 1969 is somewhat sparse.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions. Recordings are original; listening copies need to be made for use.
Acquisitions Information
Transferred in 1969 and 1981.
Historical Note
The Center for Advanced Studies (CAS) was founded at Wesleyan University in 1959 and existed until 1969. Wesleyan appears to be the first liberal arts college to create such a center. The CAS invited fellows to reside at Wesleyan and participate in the intellectual life of the campus. Each year, the fellows were a diverse group of academics, scientists, social scientists, writers, artists, and other intellectuals.
In a memo to the faculty announcing the creation of the center, President Victor Butterfield wrote: We feel that institutions of Wesleyan's type, if they can find the resources, should on principle support vigorously the creative work of some of our very ablest people in the liberating disciplines. We feel particularly that such people should be drawn not only from abroad as well as from home, but from the so-called 'active' as well as scholarly professions. One of our concerns and one of the nation's persisting and serious problems is the cultural gap in our society between the intellectual and the man of affairs. We feel that each of these types has much to learn from the other, that they should come together more often in serious discourse, and that the liberal institution should support the study and writing of our ablest journalists, justices, ministers, industrialists and the like, as well as of professional scholars and creative artists.
The Center for Advanced Studies building was housed in Olin library until fall 1960 when it moved into a new building behind the Russell House on Pearl Street (the same building where the Center for the Humanities was later located). Fellows stayed for a full school year, a semester, or a period of weeks, depending on scheduling. During their residence at Wesleyan, fellows were encouraged to research and write but also to work with undergraduate students within Wesleyan departments. They often gave lectures and seminars about their specialties, or even offered courses. The fellows were provided with residences for themselves and their families and given a stipend. Most fellows were men, but several women were also invited, including Hannah Arendt and Jean Stafford.
Sigmund Neumann served as director of CAS from 1959-1962, Paul Horgan from 1962 until 1967, and Phillip Hallie as acting director from 1967-1969. Suggestions for fellows were accepted from all members of the Wesleyan community. Fellows were selected by a panel consisting of the president of the university, the director of CAS, and a trustee. Their decisions were presented to the faculty for approval. Monday evening dinners provided opportunities for fellows and faculty to mingle throughout the year. Wednesday afternoon open houses were sponsored by CAS to bring fellows and students together. Among the fellows to reside at CAS were Hannah Arendt, John Cage, Daniel P. Moynihan, Leslie Munro, and Richard Wilbur.
Beginning in 1968, the fellows were chosen for their similarity of interests in order to allow them to collaborate and to connect with the Wesleyan community in greater depth. At the end of 1968, plans were made to convert the Center for Advanced Studies into a Center for the Humanities. This change was partially the result of the Study for Educational Policies and Programs (SEPP) conducted in early 1968. The major changes included a selection process administered by a board that included faculty, students, and administrators; required teaching responsibilities; and the selection of a broad issue in which the scholars would focus their research. These changes, and the new name, took effect in fall 1969.
Chronology of Fellows
1959-1960 Alan Willard Brown Reuel N. Denney Herbert McLean Evans Paul Horgan C. I. Lewis William Manchester Clarence Belden Randall Nathan Shapira
1960-1961 Edgar Anderson Reginald Francis Arragon Marston Bates Julius Seelye Bixler John Cage Walter Van Tilburg Clark Austin Farrer Alvin Harvey Hansen Paul Gray Hoffman Leonard Bernheim Meyer Sir Leslie Knox Munro Sir Ronald Syme Conrad Hal Waddington Lancelot Law Whyte Alfred Hector Williams
1961-1962 Hannah Arendt Julius Seelye Bixler Brand Blanshard George Boas Douglass Cater Gilbert Harrison Clee Paul Horgan Pamela Hansford Johnson Walter J. Ong, S. J. Tibor Rado Sir Charles Percy Snow
1962-1963 Hannah Arendt Balasaraswati Richard Walker Bolling Kay Boyle John Lackey Brown Harry Caplan Douglass Cater Angna Enters Torsten Gardlund Philip Paul Hallie Erik Holmberg Abraham Kaplan Paul Patrick Streeten
1963-1964 Ernst Bacon Harry Caplan Christopher Derrick Rene Jules Dubos William H. Halewood Arthur Lennart Kalleberg John Frank Kermode Hans Kohn Terence Martin Lewis Mumford Aage Peterson Sir Herbert Read Donald H. Reiman Carl E. Schorske Ernest J. Simmons
1964-1965 Luigi Barzini, Jr. Martin J. Buss Herbert Butterfield John Leonard Clendenning Very Rev. Martin Cyril D'Arcy, S.J. Wayne Donald Dodd Rene Jules Dubos Moses Hadas Hiram Haydn Hans Jones John Bartlow Martin Willard Van Orman Quine Sir Herbert Read Jean Stafford Edmund Wilson
1965-1966 Harold Gomes Cassidy Leon Edel Mircea Eliade Jesse Hill Ford Anne Fremantle Richard N. Goodwin Sergio Gutierrez Olivos Daniel P. Moynihan Sean O'Faolain Michael Polanyi Ernest J. Simmons
1966-1967 William Arrowsmith John Buxton Joseph Elder Robert Fuller Richard N. Goodwin Sergio Gutierrez Olivos Thomas Messer J. A. Richards Stephen Spender Rev. George Tavard
1967-1968 Arvid Brodersen Hans Magnus Enzensberger Paul Horgan Gorham Munson Lawrence Clark Powell Edward Weismiller Richard Wilbur Huseyn Yilmaz Ralph Young
1968-1969 Lucien Goldmann Paul Horgan Herbert H. Hyman Howard Robinson Theodore Sarbin Petrus J. Verdoorn
Collection Overview
The Center for Advanced Studies Records consists of four series: Administrative Files, Fellows, Persons Under Consideration, and Recordings. Throughout the collection, documentation from 1967 to 1969 is somewhat sparse. In some cases, the original file folders have been retained to preserve documentation on them.
The Administrative Files include annual reports, conference and seminar information, correspondence, publicity documents, photographs, and Monday Evening Papers, which were brief publications based on evening lectures given by the fellows.
The Fellows series is an alphabetical listing of some (but not all) of the fellows of the CAS. Folders typically contain correspondence, lists of accomplishments while in residence, newspaper clippings, and resumes, among other documents. The Persons Under Consideration series is an alphabetical listing of people suggested or self-nominated to the selectors. Folders in this series typically include correspondence and memoranda.
The Recordings series contains audio tape recordings and transcripts of some of the recordings. These were typically speeches or interviews given by fellows or at CAS events.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Center for Advanced Studies.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Butterfield, Victor Lloyd, 1904-; Hallie, Philip Paul.; Neumann, Sigmund.; Horgan, Paul, 1903-1995.; Humanities -- Study and teaching.; Research institutes.; Social sciences--Study and teaching.; Scrapbooks.; Science--Study and teaching.; Photographs.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative files are arranged alphabetically.
  - American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) Fellows
    - General Correspondence, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Martin Buss, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John Clendenning, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Wayne Dodd, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - William H. Halewood, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Arthur L. Kalleberg, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Terence Martin, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Donald H. Reiman, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes Fellows' Reports.
    - 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Material for annual reports, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appointments and general information
    - 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Budget/Endowment, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Budget Proposal, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chapbooks numbers 1, 2, and 3, correspondence regarding, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, fellows and general, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence
    - Butterfield, Victor, regarding CAS Fellows, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Edwin Etherington, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Memorandums from Paul Horgan to Victor Butterfield, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Paul Horgan, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Paul Horgan, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Memo regarding visiting professors, circa 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Events
    - Conference on Excellence and Leadership in a Democracy, April 28-30, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Dr. Sigmund Neumann's Speech at the Free University, Berlin, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Symposium: The City, January 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Conference on Humanistic Psychology, November 27-29, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Celebration in honor of Paul Horgan, February 12, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Evening in honor of Michael Polanyi, April 9, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Evening in honor of Paul Horgan, January 4, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Kaprow's Happenings, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Movie Conference, February 10-11, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Visit of Surgeon General, March 18, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Science Center Conference, April 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Symposium on Problems of Contemporary Spanish Literature in Exile, April 20, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Conference: The Urban Crisis in America, May 1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Forum: How Can Our Institutions Deal Effectively with Social Change? September 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Forum: How Can Our Institutions Deal Effectively with Social Change? manuscript: What do we mean? A young approach to institutional changes, Edward Hayes and Richard Gross, September 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Seminar: The Black Church in America, October 1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Conference on Humanities and Social Sciences, January 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fellows
    - Concerts, 1964-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dinners, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Memos to Fellows, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Honors College
    - Annual Report, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Honors College/CAS Coordination, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Honors College/CAS Coordination drafts, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Lectures, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Housing
    - Housing and office assignments, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Housing and office (including Honors College), 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Housing and office assignments, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Housing, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Summer use of, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Summer use of by National Science Foundation, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Fellows and living conditions, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Ideas, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Inquiries
    - 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Junior Fellows/Collegiate Fellows, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - (CAS) Library Accession Record (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lists of books written by fellows (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Monday Evenings, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Monday Evening Papers (Volume 1)
    The collection of Monday Evening Papers is gathered in a single enclosure not housed in box 5.
    - Number 1: The Astronomer's Universe--Reality or Delusion? by Eric Holberg, 1965
    - Number 2: On Shakespeare's Learning by Frank Kermode, 1965
    - Number 3: High Noon and Darkest Night by Herbert Read, 1964
    - Number 4: Style the Repository by Moses Hadas, 1965
    - Number 5: T. S. E.--A Memoir by Herbert Read, 1966
    - Number 6: On Some Scientific Concepts in Russian Poetry at the Turn of the Century, by F. D. Reeve, 1966
    - Number 7: The Age of the Archive, by Leon Edel, 1966
    - Number 8: Cultural Fashions and History of Religions, by Mircea Eliade, 1967
    - Number 9: Montaigne, and Philosophy as Self-Portraiture, by Philip P. Hallie, 1966
    - Number 10: Traffic Safety and the Health of the Body Politic, by Daniel P. Moynihan, 1966
    - Number 11: Byron and Shelley: A Friendship Renewed, by John Buxton, 1967
    - Number 12: Animals in Exile: Imagery and Theme in Capote's In Cold Blood, by George R. Creeger, 1967
    - Number 13: Causal and Moral Law: Their Relationship as Examined in Terms of a Model of the Brain, by Robert W. Fuller, 1967
    - Number 14: Post Scriptum: Paul Klee at the Guggenheim Museum, by Thomas M. Messer, 1968
    - Number 15: Serpent's Progress: The Writing of a Novel, by Edward Weismiller, 1968
    - Number 16: Horror and the Paradox of Cruelty, by Philip P. Hallie, 1969
    - Number 17: Maurice Baring Reconsidered, by Paul Horgan, 1968
    - Number 18: The Myth of the Criminal Type, by Theodore R. Sarbin, 1969
    - The Sense of the Center, 1969
  - Monday Evenings, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Monday Evening Papers mailing lists (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Open house invitation, October 8, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets, 1959-1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Parties, circa 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Photographs
    - Album, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Album, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Photographs (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Plans: Early building plans, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Plans: Early plans for program, policy, building, publicity, and nomination for fellowships, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Policy notes, circa 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Public relations
    - Memos on Future Notes, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Notes from the Center, number 1, 1959-1963 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes from the Center, number 2, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Publicity
    - 1961 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - circa 1962-1967 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Roster, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1962-1969 (Box 25)
    Includes announcements and invitations to lectures, dinners, and concerts given by fellows of the Center for Advanced Studies.
  - Student teas, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Student teas, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - University Relations, 1964-1968 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Visitors to the Center, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Fellows
  The Fellows series is arranged alphabetically. The dates indicate the years in which the person was a fellow, but materials within the folder may be dated before or after that time.
  - Anderson, Edgar, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arendt, Hannah, 1961-1962, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Arragon, R. F., 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Arrowsmith, William, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bacon, Ernst, 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Balasaraswati, S. and her family, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Barzini, Luigi, November 22, 1964- December 5, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Bates, Marston, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bixler, J. Seelye, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Blanshard, Brand, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Boas, George, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Bolling, Richard, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Boyle, Kay, 1962-1963 (second semester) (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Brodersen, A., 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Alan, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Brown, John L., 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Butterfield, Herbert, March 10, 1965-April 22, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Buxton, John, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Cage, John, 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Caplan, Harry, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Also a visiting fellow in January 1964.
  - Cassidy, Harold, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Cater, Douglass, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    Also Associate Director, 1963-1964, 1964-1965
  - Clark, Walter Van Tilburg, 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Clee, Gil, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - D'Arcy, Rev. Fr. Martin, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Denney, Reuel, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Derrick, Christopher, 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - DuBos, Rene, 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Edel, Leon, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Elder, Joseph, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Enters, Angna, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Enzenberger, H., 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Evans, Herbert, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Farrer, Austin, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Ford, Jesse Hill, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Freemantle, Anne, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Fuller, Robert, 1966-1967 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Gardlund, Torsten, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Goodwin, Richard, 1965-1966 (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Gutierrez Olivos, Sergio, 1965-1966, 1966-1967 (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Hadas, Moses, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Hallie, Philip, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Hansen, Alvin, 1960-1961 (second semester) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Haydn, Hiram, 1964-1965 (first semester) (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Hoffman, Paul G., 1961 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Holmberg, Erik B., 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Horgan, Paul, 1959-1960 (second semester) (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Horgan, Paul, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Horgan publicity (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Jonas, Hans, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Kaplan, Abe, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Kermore, Frank, 1963-1964 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Kohn, Hans, 1963-1964 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Lewis, C. I., visiting lecturer, October 1959 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Manchester, William, 1959-1960 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Martin, John B., 1963-1964, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Martin, John B. and the Dominican Republic (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Messer, Thomas, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Meyer, Leonard, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Moynihan, Daniel P., 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Mumford, Lewis, Fall 1963-1964 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Munro, Sir Leslie, 1960-1961 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Munson, G., 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - O'Faolain, Sean, April 1966-May 1966 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Ong, Father Walter Jackson, S. J., 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Peterson, Ange, 1963-1964 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Polanyi, Michael, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
  - Polanyi, Michael, April 9, 1966 party and miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Powell, L. C., 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Quine, W. V., 1964-1965 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Rado, Tibor, 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Randall, C. B., 1959-1960 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Read, Sir Herbert, 1963-1964 and March-June 1965 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Richards, T. A., 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Robinson, Howard T., 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Sarbin, Theodore, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Schorske, Carl, 1963-1964 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Shapira, Nathan, 1959-1960 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Simmons, Frank T., 1963-1964, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
  - Snow, C. P., 1961-1962 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Snow, Lady, 1961-1962 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Spender, Stephen, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Stafford, Jean (Mrs. A. J. Liebling), 1964-1965 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Streeten, Paul, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Syme, Sir Ronald, 1960-1961 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Tavard, Rev. George, 1966-1967 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Waddington, C. H., 1960-1961 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Weismiller, Edward, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Whyte, Lancelot, 1960-1961 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Wilbur, R., 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Williams, Alfred H. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1964-1965 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Yilmaz, H. 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Young, Ralph, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Persons Under Consideration
  The Persons Under Consideration series is arranged alphabetically. The dates indicate the years in which the person was a considered for a fellowship.
  - A: general (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Abrams, Meyer (Mike) H., 1959-1962 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Alekseyev (Alexeiff), M. P., 1963 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Ashby, Sir Eric, 1960-1964 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Avon, Lord (The Rt. Hon., the Earl of) (Anthony Eden), 1965 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Auden, W. H., 1967 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - B: general (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
  - Barati, George, 1964-1967 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Barnes, W. H. F., 1963 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Baron, Hans, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Barr, Alfred, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Barthes, Roland, 1963-1967 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Bergin, Thomas, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Berlinski, Herman, circa 1960-1962 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Bernstein, Leonard, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Biggs, Hon. John, Jr. 1965 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Bitter, Francis, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Blackett, P. M. S., 1963-1964 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Blaisdell, Thomas, circa 1965 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Blotner, Joseph, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Bradley, Wilmot H., 1963 (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Bronowski, Jacob, 1958-1967 (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Brown, Sterling, 1963-1965 (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - Buchdahl, Gerd, 1960-1963 (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - Bullen, Keith Edward, 1962-1963 (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - Bullock, Alan, 1959-1964 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Bundy, McGeorge (Dean), 1959 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Bunker, Ellsworth, 1965-1966 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Butler, David, 1960-1963 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - C: general (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Calhoun, Robert L., 1962-1965 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Carter, Gwen, 1960-1962 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Cecil, Lord David, 1959-1965 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Chagas, Carlos, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Chakravarty, Amiya, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Chance, Michael, R.A., 1959 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Chang, Chung-yuan, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 12)